Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

Department of Psychology, The Ohio State University

I am currently a doctoral candidate in quantitative psychology at the Ohio State University. My research is focused on latent variable modelling and its applications to behavioral, neuroimaging, and bioinformatics data. I hold a master's degree in mathematical statistics and I have a strong background in machine learning, multivariate statistics, and scientific computing. I am passionate about the open access movement in education, research, and academia and I am dedicated to rigorous science in the public interest.

Education

Academic Qualifications.....

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

2015-Present

PhD in Quantitative Psychology Advisor: Professor Robert Cudeck

Dissertation Topic: 'Deep Latent Generative Models'

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

Master of Science in Statistics [GPA 3.80/4]

2012-2014

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

Master's Degree in Quantitative Psychology

2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modelling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

The Pennsylvania State University

Pennsylvania, USA

 $^{\circ}$ Bachelor's Degree in Psychology with High Distinction [GPA 3.93/4]

2011-2012

Course Projects....

- **Multivariate Statistics** (STAT 7560): 'Retinotopic Mapping of the Human Visual Cortex Using Independent Component Analysis'
- Advanced Computational Statistics (STAT 7730): 'Bayesian Analysis of Noisy Images Using Markov Random Fields'
- **Statistical Consulting** (STAT 6750): 'Modelling Categorical Perception of Speech Sounds using Beta Regression'

Experience

Internship	
The Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program Research Lab of Professor Ewy Mathé, The Ohio State University	m (BMI SIP) 2016
Project : Developing an R package for ATAC-seq and DHS-seq data analy visualization of regulatory gene transcription pathways involved in cancer expressions.	
Teaching Experience	
Graduate Teaching Associate The Ohio State University Teaching Assistant for Psychology 2220: Data Analysis in Psychology	Ohio, USA 2013–present
Test Preparation Instructor Instructor of the Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT)	Moscow, Russia 2009-2012
Teacher of English as a Foreign Language Teacher of General and Academic English	Moscow, Russia 2001-2009
Journal Review Service.	
Psychometrika Ad Hoc Reviewer	2015
Psychological Methods Ad Hoc Reviewer	2016
Conference Presentations	
Joint Statistical Meetings Operator Presentation	Seattle 2015
Poster Title : Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Response sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model	es to Faces using a
Awards and Fellowships	
Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University	2015
The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellow The Ohio State University	vship 2015
Project Proposal : 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'	

The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2014

University Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2012

Technical Skill Set

Statistics and Machine Learning

- **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python*, and *Julia* depending on computing goals.
- Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Tensorflow and MXNet.
- Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan; Familiar with Venture.

Computer Science

- Cluster and High-Performance Computing: Good knowledge of running numerical analyses on the Ohio Supercomputer. Basic familiarity with distributed cluster computing using the Spark platform.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

Domain Specific Software

- Neuroimaging Analysis Software: Nipype, PyMVPA, FreeSurfer, and Pycortex.
- **Bioinformatics Software:** Experienced in analysing functional genomics data (i.e. RNA-seq) using R's Bioconductor set of tools. HarvardX PH525 MOOC class series taken:
 - · Data Analysis for Life Sciences 4: High-Dimensional Data Analysis
 - · Data Analysis for Life Sciences 5: Introduction to Bioconductor
 - Data Analysis for Life Sciences 6: High-performance Computing for Reproducible Genomics
 - Data Analysis for Life Sciences 7: Case Studies in Functional Genomics

Personal Details

- o Country of Previous Residence: Russia (12 years)
- o Marital Status: Married
- o Interests and Hobbies: Evolutionary Biology, World Cuisines, Experimental Music
- o Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (limited)